Today's daf is כ"ו, Chaf-Vav, בבא קמא Baba Kamma 26, and we
pick up at the very bottom of כ"ה עמוד ב', Chaf-Hei Amud
Bet,
and we pick up with ותהא שן ורגל, Ve-Tei Shen Ve-Regel, the
very end of the last of the narrowest lines, and our learning
should be in the זכות Zachut of the ongoing return of all
of the hostages that were part of the deal and of all
of the hostages and their safety and security and well-being. Okay, so
we're in the middle of the whole discussion about דיו Dayo for
רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, and we said that for רבי טרפון Rabbi
Tarfon he does not hold of דיו Dayo if it would undermine
the קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, if the קל וחומר Kal Vachomer wouldn't
get you anything more than you started with, and in that case
you're allowed to use the קל וחומר Kal Vachomer to go even
beyond your original case, but presumably
taking indication from parallel cases how far you can extend it. So
חצי נזק Chatzi Nezek we're able to upgrade to נזק שלם Nezek
Shalem in רשות הניזק Reshut Ha-Nizak because otherwise we wouldn't learn anything
from the קל וחומר Kal Vachomer and because שן ורגל Shen Ve-Regel
pay full amount in רשות
הניזק. Reshut Ha-Nizak. Now the גמרא Gemara continues.
ותהא שן ורגל חייב ברשות הרבים מקל וחומר. Ve-Tei Shen Ve-Regel Chayav
Bi-Reshut Ha-Rabim Mi-Kal Vachomer. Now that we are done with the whole
דיו Dayo discussion, we're going to discuss how you might use קל
וחומר Kal Vachomer looking at שן ורגל Shen Ve-Regel on one hand
and קרן Keren on the other side. So it says, why not
say שן ורגל Shen Ve-Regel are חייב Chayav in רשות הרבים Reshut
Ha-Rabim from a קל וחומר? Kal Vachomer? This is now even according
to the רבנן. Rabbanan. Forget רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon for the moment.
ומה קרן שברשות הניזק אינו משלם אלא חצי נזק. U-Mah Keren She-Bi-Reshut
Ha-Nizak Eino Meshalem Ela Chatzi Nezek.
So by קרן, Keren, this is according to the רבנן Rabbanan in
the רשות הניזק Reshut Ha-Nizak you pay half damages. So if that's
true for the
Rabbis, ברשות הרבים חייבת Bi-Reshut Ha-Rabim Chayavet and in רשות הרבים Reshut
Ha-Rabim you also pay half. So קרן Keren is half in רשות
הניזק, Reshut Ha-Nizak, half in רשות הרבים. Reshut Ha-Rabim. So שן ורגל
שברשות הניזק משלם נזק שלם. Shen Ve-Regel She-Bi-Reshut Ha-Nizak Meshalem Nezek Shalem.
So שן ורגל Shen Ve-Regel that in the רשות הניזק Reshut Ha-Nizak
in the damagee's domain, in the private domain, is full amount. So
שן ורגל Shen Ve-Regel is certainly more than, weightier in רשות הניזק
Reshut Ha-Nizak than קרן Keren is. You pay full rather than half.
אינו דין שברשות הרבים חייב? Eino Din She-Bi-Reshut Ha-Rabim Chayav? Should you
not at least in רשות הרבים Reshut Ha-Rabim be חייב? Chayav? Maybe
חייב Chayav half, maybe חייב Chayav all, but anyway, so if you're
חייב Chayav by
קרן, Keren, קרן Keren you're חייב Chayav in
רשות הניזק Reshut Ha-Nizak and you're חייב Chayav in רשות הרבים, Reshut
Ha-Rabim, so שן ורגל Shen Ve-Regel that you're חייב Chayav in רשות
הניזק Reshut Ha-Nizak full, shouldn't there also be some degree of חיוב
Chiyuv in רשות הרבים Reshut Ha-Rabim if you use קל וחומר? Kal
Vachomer? אמר קרא, Amar Kra, so the פסוק Pasuk responds, so the
answer is no, you can't say that because the פסוק Pasuk says
ובער בשדה אחר U-Ve-Eir Bi-Sdeh Acher and not ברשות הרבים. Bi-Reshut Ha-Rabim.
The פסוק Pasuk is very clear that the obligation is only when
it consumes in another field and not in רשות הרבים. Reshut Ha-Rabim.
In רשות הרבים Reshut Ha-Rabim it is going to be exempt, there
is no basis for חיוב Chiyuv in רשות הרבים Reshut Ha-Rabim for
שן ורגל. Shen Ve-Regel. Top of כ"ו עמוד א'. Chaf-Vav Amud Aleph.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, מידי כולי קאמינא פלגא קאמינא.
Midi Kulei Ka-Amina Palga Ka-Amina. I'm not saying you should pay full,
I'm saying you should pay half. So the פסוק, Pasuk, you're right,
the פסוק Pasuk says that שן ורגל Shen Ve-Regel are obligated ובער
בשדה אחר U-Ve-Eir Bi-Sdeh Acher to pay the full amount. And that's
what it tells you, full amount in רשות הניזק. Reshut Ha-Nizak. It
doesn't tell you רשות הרבים. Reshut Ha-Rabim. Let's use a קל וחומר
Kal Vachomer to tell me if קרן Keren pays half in רשות
הרבים, Reshut Ha-Rabim, certainly שן ורגל Shen Ve-Regel should pay half in
רשות הרבים. Reshut Ha-Rabim. אמר קרא, Amar Kra, so the גמרא Gemara
responds, the Torah says no, וחצו את כספו, Ve-Chatzu Et Kaspo, כספו
של זה ולא כספו של אחר. Kaspo Shel Zeh Ve-Lo Kaspo Shel
Acher. The Torah says by קרן Keren you should divide the value,
half payment only occurs by קרן Keren and it does not occur
by anything else. So therefore full you don't pay clearly because the
פסוק Pasuk says full is only in רשות הניזק Reshut Ha-Nizak and
half you don't pay because half is being labeled as something that
is unique to קרן. Keren. You might remember that of course חצי
נזק צרורות Chatzi Nezek Tzerorot but that's הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Le-Moshe
Mi-Sinai. A קל וחומר Kal Vachomer can't get us that because the
פסוקים Pesukim are clear that at least as far as, you know,
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha Le-Moshe Mi-Sinai aside, from the פסוקים Pesukim perspective,
the only thing that you're paying half for is going to be
קרן. Keren. ולא כספו של אחר. Ve-Lo Kaspo Shel Acher. Now of
course what's worth mentioning here, which also always has to be mentioned
by קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, is that a קל וחומר Kal Vachomer
ignores unique characteristics of each case to explain their differences. Right, logically
you could say שן ורגל Shen Ve-Regel because they're much more prevalent
and common, that's why you're exempt in רשות הרבים Reshut Ha-Rabim totally.
Either because people have to live their lives and be able to
take their animals in רשות הרבים Reshut Ha-Rabim or because there's פשיעה
הניזק. Pshia Ha-Nizak. The person who's leaving his stuff out in רשות
הרבים Reshut Ha-Rabim should be aware that there are animals around so
he has also contributory negligence. Whereas
קרן, Keren, goring is unlikely, so therefore there is no need to
exempt קרן Keren in רשות הרבים Reshut Ha-Rabim and there's no
פשיעה הניזק. Pshia Ha-Nizak. There's no need to exempt קרן Keren in
רשות הרבים Reshut Ha-Rabim but there is a need to exempt שן
ורגל. Shen Ve-Regel. So there's a particular logic to exempt. Whereas when
you do רשות הניזק... Reshut Ha-Nizak... Because קרן Keren is half because
it's unlikely, and שן Shen and רגל, Regel, there is a high
degree of negligence. So there's a logic why שן Shen and רגל
Regel is full in רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak, high degree of negligence.
פטור Patur in רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim, either you need a general
allowance, public policy type of thing, or contributory negligence. And קרן, Keren,
which is unusual, is going to be half in all places. Okay,
so there's a logic for those differences, but קל וחומר Kal Vachomer
ignores particular characteristics, how they might be tied to particular הלכות. Halachot.
It just looks in a very simplistic way: what's the weight, how
heavy is it, and what is the payment. So based on that
קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, we wanted to say pay half for שן
Shen and רגל Regel in רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim, and we say
no, the פסוק Pasuk says half payment is only by קרן. Keren.
Okay, כספו של זה ולא כספו של אחר. Kaspo shel zeh velo
kaspo shel acher. Now, three lines from the top, continuing: ולא תהא
שן ורגל חייבת ברשות הניזק אלא חצי נזק מקל וחומר. Velo tehei
Shen v'Regel chayaves b'Reshut HaNizak ela chatzi nezek mi'Kal Vachomer. Fine,
let's go the reverse. Let's say that you'll only pay half damages
for שן Shen and רגל Regel in the רשות הניזק. Reshut HaNizak.
Why? Based on a קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer. מקרן. Mi'Keren. ומה. U'mah.
So now the קל וחומר Kal Vachomer is going to say that
it's going to be less. Okay. ומה קרן שברשות הרבים חייבת ברשות
הניזק אינו משלם אלא חצי נזק. U'mah Keren she'b'Reshut HaRabim chayaves b'Reshut
HaNizak eino m'shalem ela chatzi nezek.
קרן, Keren, which is weighty, that you pay in רשות הרבים, Reshut
HaRabim, in רשות הניזק Reshut HaNizak you only pay half. שן ורגל
שברשות הרבים פטורה, Shen v'Regel she'b'Reshut HaRabim p'turah, שן Shen and רגל
Regel which is lighter, because in רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim you don't
pay for שן Shen and רגל, Regel, so if it's a less
weighty case, שן Shen and רגל, Regel, so אינו דין שברשות הניזק
משלם חצי נזק? eino din she'b'Reshut HaNizak m'shalem chatzi nezek? How much
more so in רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak, if שן Shen and רגל
Regel is less weighty than קרן Keren because it's exempt in רשות
הרבים, Reshut HaRabim, and קרן, Keren, the weightier case, you pay only
half in רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak, how much more so should שן
Shen and רגל, Regel, the less weighty case, you also only pay
half in רשות הניזק? Reshut HaNizak? Again, ignoring the unique characteristics.
So the גמרא Gemara says אינו משלם... so... שן ורגל Shen v'Regel
שברשות הרבים פטורה אינו דין שברשות הניזק משלם חצי נזק? Nezek אמר
קרא, Amar Kra, so the answer to this is that the פסוק
Pasuk says: ישלם. Yishalem. וביער בשדה אחר, U'vi'er b'sdeh acher, it says
מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו ישלם. m'tav sadeh u'm'tav kramo yishalem. You shall
compensate. So the word compensate, compensation, means תשלומין מעליא, Tashlumin Maalya, full
compensation.
So those are not variable. We know שן Shen and רגל Regel
full in רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak, zero in רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim.
And קרן Keren we know half in both places if we reject
רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: תשלומין מעליא. Tashlumin Maalya. ולא תהא קרן ברשות הרבים חייב מקל
וחומר. Velo tehei Keren b'Reshut HaRabim chayav mi'Kal Vachomer.
So now let's try to exempt קרן Keren from רשות הרבים Reshut
HaRabim from a קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer. מה שן ורגל שברשות הניזק
נזק שלם, Mah Shen v'Regel she'b'Reshut HaNizak nezek shalem,
שן Shen and רגל Regel is weightier, that you pay in רשות
הניזק Reshut HaNizak full, ברשות הרבים פטור b'Reshut HaRabim patur and you're
still exempt in רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. קרן שברשות הניזק חצי נזק,
Keren she'b'Reshut HaNizak chatzi nezek,
קרן Keren that according to the רבנן Rabbanan is only half damages,
so קרן Keren is less weighty in רשות הניזק. Reshut HaNizak. So
if that's true, that only half, so therefore ברשות הרבים פטור, b'Reshut
HaRabim patur, then in רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim it should be exempt
the same way שן Shen and רגל, Regel, which is weightier in
רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak, is exempt in רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. קרן,
Keren, which is less weighty in רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak, should be
fully exempt in רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim as well. So אינו דין
שברשות הרבים פטור? eino din she'b'Reshut HaRabim patur? אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar
Rabbi Yochanan, אמר קרא, amar Kra, the פסוק Pasuk says: יחצון. Yechetzun.
וגם את המת יחצון, Ve'gam es ha'meis yechetzun,
you should divide. And it could have just said וגם את המת,
ve'gam es ha'meis, because it already said divide the money and it
could have said and also the corpse. So why does it say
יחצון, yechetzun, that they divide? אין חצי נזק חלוק. Ein chatzi nezek
chaluk. To tell you that half damages is going to apply in
all places. לא ברשות הרבים ולא ברשות היחיד. Lo b'Reshut HaRabim velo
b'Reshut HaYachid.
Whether in רשות הרבים Reshut HaRabim or רשות היחיד, Reshut HaYachid, it's
always going to be half. Okay. So we keep everything the way
we knew it. קרן Keren is half whether in רשות הרבים Reshut
HaRabim or רשות היחיד Reshut HaYachid or רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak, and
שן Shen ורגל is full in רשות הניזק Reshut HaNizak and zero
in רשות הרבים. Reshut HaRabim. And we don't use קל וחומר. Kal
Vachomers. A: because the characteristics explain the differences. But if we're going
to deal with the more simplistic קל וחומר Kal Vachomer weighty, less
weighty, etc., we have פסוקים Pesukim that tell me keep those exactly
the way you understood them to be. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay. ותהא אדם חייב
בכופר. Ve'hei adam chayav b'kofer.
Now we're moving beyond שן and רגל. Regel. Let's say a person
who murders somebody should be חייב chayav in a כופר kofer מקל
וחומר, mi'Kal Vachomer, from a קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer. What's the קל
וחומר? Kal Vachomer? ומה שור שאינו חייב בארבעה דברים חייב בכופר. U'mah
shor she'eino chayav b'arbah devarim chayav b'kofer. An ox that if it
gores a human being and causes injury, it only pays damages, it
doesn't pay the other four things: צער נזק ריפוי שבת
ובושת. tza'ar, nezek, ripuy, shevet, u-boshet. Pain, doctors' bills, time off of
work, and the embarrassment. That only is by a human that causes
injury to another human, not by an ox that causes injury to
a human. So an ox is less weighty. ומה שאינו חייב בארבעה
דברים חייב בכופר, U'mah she'eino chayav b'arbah devarim chayav b'kofer,
has to pay כופר kofer if the ox kills a human and
has done it three times, then it... and then you would not
only stone the ox, but you would pay כופר kofer? *kofer*, pay
an atonement payment for the life. אדם adam *Adam*, when a person
injures another person, שחייב בארבעה דברים *she’chayav b'arba'ah devarim*, and the person
is the injurer, so then and you know another person is the
injuree, you pay the additional four payments of שבת, Shabbos ריפוי, צער,
tza'ar ובושת *shevet, ripui, tza'ar, u’voshet*. So if that's weightier when a
human being causes damage, so אינו דין שחייב בכופר *eino din she'chayav
b'kofer*, how much more so should if a human being murder that
he should also pay an atonement payment, a כופר kofer *kofer* payment?
So אמר קרא amar kra, *amar kra*, no, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
says, ככל אשר יושת עליו *k'chol asher yushas alav*, you should pay
all that is placed on him when the ox does the goring
and kills a person, עליו ולא על אדם adam *alav v'lo al
adam*, on the ox or on the owner of the ox or
whatever, but not on a human who actually takes a life. Now
by the way, the הוה אמינא *hava amina* that a person should
pay כופר kofer *kofer* is a little strange because normally we have
principles of like קים ליה בדרבה מיניה *kam lei b'drabba minei*, that
you don't pay two payments when you do a something that is
a capital crime. Nevertheless, here קים ליה בדרבה מיניה *kam lei b'drabba
minei* is when there's an external payment, you don't also pay it
if you've also done a capital crime. The possibility here though is
is that the actual capital crime itself should come with two punishments;
it should come both with killing the person and it should also
come with the fact that he should actually have to pay damages
or כופר kofer? *kofer*. And that's what's being excluded. רש"י Rashi, *Rashi*
says, by the way, we're talking about a case that you wouldn't
execute the person and he wouldn't get גלות galus, *galus*, like he
would be a case of מזיד meizid *meizid*, intentional, but there wouldn't
be התראה *hasra'ah*, so he wouldn't actually get any other payment. That
doesn't totally get you out of the קים ליה בדרבה מיניה *kam
lei b'drabba minei* question, because even if it's a type of a
sin that would be deserving under other circumstances of a capital crime
that normally overrides monetary payments, so that's not only the point here,
you know, maybe the point is also that we don't this is
not an external payment, maybe this would be always coming alongside or
maybe at least coming with a capital with murder when the person
wasn't being executed, maybe that would be what the תורה Torah, *Torah*
would indicate would be the proper punishment
or you know when when a person actually commits murder. So that's
the question: maybe there should always be two aspects of murder, the
capital crime plus payment and the damages, and the answer is no,
that's only for a שור *shor* is there an idea of a
כופר kofer *kofer*. By the way, in the case of a שור
*shor*, it most likely is not about damages, it's about being deserving
of at some virtual level the death penalty because you let your
ox who you knew was a גורר *gorer* go out and you
weren't careful and it killed yet again, so to some degree you're
deserving of the death penalty and therefore it's saying that you can
give this כופר kofer *kofer* to atone for it. Okay, but at
least when we thought to apply it to a case of a
human who committed murder or manslaughter, whatever, it would have been logically
not an atonement payment as much as damages alongside the capital crime,
but the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* rejects that. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* continues: ויהא
*v'yehai*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ויהא שור חייב chayav בארבעה דברים
מקל וחומר *v'yehai shor chayav b'arba'ah devarim m'kal vachomer*. Ah, now that
an ox is weightier that it pays כופר kofer *kofer* and a
human doesn't, let's use a קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer* to
say that an ox gores a man it pays the additional four
payments. ויהא שור חייב chayav. בארבעה דברים מקל וחומר. מה אדם adam;
שאינו חייב chayav בכופר חייב chayav, בארבעה דברים *v'yehai shor chayav b'arba'ah
devarim m'kal vachomer. Mah adam she’eino chayav b'kofer chayav b'arba'ah devarim*, a
human being who kills a human does not pay כופר kofer, *kofer*,
still has to pay these four additional payments of damages when it's
not a death, okay, שבת, Shabbos ריפוי, צער, tza'ar. ובושת *shevet, ripui,
tza'ar, u’voshet*. שור שחייב בכופר *Shor she'chayav b'kofer*, an ox that gores
a human and kills it that pays כופר kofer *kofer*, so it's
weightier and that it pays כופר kofer *kofer*, אינו דין שחייב בארבעה
דברים *eino din she'chayav b'arba'ah devarim*, how much more so should it
have to pay these four additional damages payments
when it causes damage to another human being because a שור *shor*
is now weightier. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר קרא איש
בעמיתו *amar kra ish b’amito*, when a man puts a wound on
another human being and from that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* we learn the
additional payments. So it says a man by his neighbor, so it
says כי יתן מום בעמיתו *ki yitein mum b'amito*, איש בעמיתו ולא
שור בעמיתו *ish b'amito v'lo shor b'amito*, not an ox with his
fellow or not an ox with a human we should say, not
exactly his fellow. But the bottom line is that the פסוקים *psukim*
from which we learn עין תחת עין ayin tachas ayin, שן תחת
שן shein tachas shein, *ayin tachat ayin shein tachat shein* or all
the other פסוקים *psukim* that we learn the additional payments, those are
all about humans damaging humans and therefore we understand it to exclude
an ox even if a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer* would
want you to include. Okay, so that's the end now of the
קל וחומרים *kal vachomerim* of the דיו dayo. *dayo* of רבי טרפון
Rabbi Tarfon. *Rabbi Tarfon* and using קל וחומרים *kal vachomerim* to try
to level the differences that we have between the נזיקין nezikin, *nezikin*.
Now we're going to ask an interesting question that seems a little
off topic, but we'll see it's directly relevant to a teaching of
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon, *Rabbi Tarfon*. איבעיא להו Iba'ya lehu: *Iba'ya lehu*,
they asked the following question: רגל שדרסה על גבי תינוק בחצר הניזק
מהו שתשלם כופר Regel she-dar'sa al gabei tinok b'chatzer ha-nizak mahu she-t'shalem
kofer? *regel she’darsah al gabi tinok b'chatzer hanizak mahu she'teshaleim kofer*? If
we know כופר kofer *kofer* is by an ox that gores and
kills three times then it kills the fourth time a human being
it pays כופר kofer, *kofer*, what if an animal killed a human
not through a קרן keren, *keren* Trying to gore, but incidentally, by
walking, you know, it was you had this big heavy animal, or
I don't know, imagine it's an elephant or an ox, it doesn't
matter, and there's a tiny little one day old infant and it
steps on it God forbid and it crushes it. So that is
a very habitual thing, that's רגל regel? for it to do. So
but it's not intending to do an act of killing and a
goring. Would there be an idea of כופר? kofer, And it depends
to some degree what you think the כופר kofer is about when
the ox gores. When the ox gores and kills a human is
the כופר kofer. because it was did it three times, it was
habitual, it was regular, there's a profound degree of negligence on the
owner's part that led to the death of a human and you
pay כופר? kofer So if that's true, there's negligence about when I
let my animal go walking in רשות הניזק, reshut hanizak, right, where
I have to be careful that it doesn't walk in other people's
domains. And there's a high degree of negligence there. And if there's
negligence for damage, there's also negligence that it could step on an
infant, right?
Or is the כופר kofer because to some degree the ox goring
is like an intentional act of murder done by my animal and
that wouldn't be relevant when it's something incidental like the case of
רגל? regel So that's the question of the גמרא. Gemara איבעיא להו:
they raised the question: רגל regel שדרסה על גבי תינוק בחצר הניזק
מהו שתשלם כופר? mahu she-t'shalem kofer? What's the story? Does it pay
כופר kofer when it goes into the another person's domain and stomps
on an infant and kills
him? מהו שתשלם כופר? kofer
מי אמרינן: mi amrinan: do we say מכדי דהוה אקרן, mikdi de-hava
a-keren, just like קרן, keren קרן כיון דעבד תרי תלתא זימני, keren
keivan de-avad terei tlata zimni, once a קרן keren has done it
two and three times, אורחיה הוא, orchei hu, it's now habitual ומשלם
כופר u-mshalem kofer and the owners pay כופר kofer because of their
negligence of allowing a death when their animal was habitual to do
things that could have brought about a death? הכא נמי לא שנא,
hacha nami lo shna, so here too exact same degree negligence, right?
It didn't need to be an act of goring. או דילמא, o
dilma, or do we say קרן כוונתו להזיק, keren kavanato l'hazik, you
know, the קרן Keren. is intending to gore והאי אין כוונתו להזיק,
ve-hai ein kavanato l'hazik, this isn't intending to do damage and therefore
it's not like a type of an act of a murder, it
was negligent and incidental but it wasn't a quasi murder. Okay. תא
שמע, ta shema, come and hear. הכניס שורו לחצר בעל הבית שלא
ברשות, hichnis shoro l'chatzer ba'al ha-bayis she-lo bi-reshus, if a person brought
his ox into his friend's property without permission, classic רשות הניזק reshut
hanizak case, ונגחו לבעל הבית ומת, u-ne-gacho l'ba'al ha-bayis va-mes, and it
gored the
owner and the owner died, השור בסקילה, ha-shor bi-skila, the ox gets
stoned obviously ובעליו בין תם בין מועד משלם כופר שלם u-be'alav bein
tam bein mu'ad meshalem kofer shalem and the and the owner and
the owners whether the ox it's the first time it killed a
human or it's habitual pays full כופר, kofer, דברי רבי טרפון. divrei
Rabbi Tarfon. That's what Rabbi Tarfon says. So here we have Rabbi
Tarfon having an ox paying כופר kofer full, you know, in רשות
הניזק. reshut hanizak. Now we know Rabbi Tarfon says you pay full
damages in רשות הניזק, reshut hanizak, but כופר kofer isn't damages, כופר
kofer is something else completely. So the question is where does he
learn that if an animal is a תם, tam, you would still
pay כופר, kofer full כופר, kofer but כופר kofer at all in
רשות הניזק? reshut hanizak? In the תורה, Torah, when an animal gores
if it's the first three times it pays and it kills someone
it pays nothing, no כופר. kofer So where does Rabbi Tarfon get
this idea that it pays כופר kofer in רשות הניזק? reshut hanizak?
So that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. Let's take a
look. דברי רבי טרפון, כופר שלם בתם לרבי טרפון מנא ליה? Divrei
Rabbi Tarfon, kofer shalem be-tam le-Rabbi Tarfon m'na lei? Where does Rabbi
Tarfon get this idea? We know he gets an idea that you
pay full damages, but where do you begin to get an idea
that you pay כופר kofer by a תם tam even if it
is in רשות הניזק? reshut hanizak? So,
so the גמרא Gemara says, מנא ליה? m'na lei? לאו משום דסבירא
ליה לרבי יוסי הגלילי, lav mishum de-savira lei le-Rabbi Yosei HaGalili,
here must be the explanation. It must be Rabbi Tarfon holds like
Rabbi Yosei HaGalili, דאמר תם משלם חצי כופר ברשות הרבים. de-amar tam
meshalem chatzi kofer bi-reshus ha-rabim. Rabbi Yosei HaGalili says the same way
a מועד mu'ad pays a full כופר kofer when it kills somebody,
a תם tam pays half כופר kofer when it kills somebody in
רשות הרבים reshut harabim because
that's when a goring animal pays. So if you started with that
assumption, then you could get to full כופר kofer in רשות הניזק
reshut hanizak by a קל וחומר. kal vachomer: Okay, that seems to
be the necessary first step. You have to have a concept of
half כופר, Kofer otherwise we never have a concept of כופר Kofer
by תם. tam. But if you have a concept of half כופר
Kofer in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, you can use Rabbi Tarfon's קל
וחומר kal vachomer. to get you to full כופר Kofer in רשות
הניזק. reshut hanizak. חצי כופר ומייתי לה מקל וחומר מרגל. Chatzi kofer
u-meisi lei mi-kal vachomer mi-regel.
And here would be the קל וחומר: kal vachomer רגל regel pays
no כופר Kofer in רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, pays full כופר Kofer
in רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak.
תם tam that pays half כופר Kofer, in רשות הרבים reshut harabim
should certainly pay full כופר Kofer, in רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak. So
you can get to תם tam paying full כופר Kofer. in רשות
הניזק reshut hanizak if you start with half כופר Kofer, in רשות
הרבים, reshut harabim, okay, and you have a קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer
But for the קל וחומר Kal Vachomer to work in the כופר
Kofer. world, you need to assume that רגל Regel pays כופר Kofer
in רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak. So the גמרא Gemara says implicit in
Rabbi Tarfon's ruling is an assumption that maybe the rabbis don't disagree
with, that רגל Regel pays כופר Kofer in רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak.
So that seems like a pretty nice argument. Let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. And it is going to be how we're going
to conclude after we try to push back. Okay, אטו איכא כופר
ברגל? Atu ika Kofer beRegel? אמר רב שימי מנהרדעא Amar Rav Shimi
miNehardea says רב שימי Rav Shimi from נהרדעא, Nehardea, אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi, תנא מנזיקין דרגל מייתי לה. Tana miNezikin deRegel maitei
lah.
No, the גמרא Gemara to make a קל וחומר Kal Vachomer you
don't need to say that רגל Regel pays כופר Kofer in רשות
הניזק. Reshut HaNizak. All you need to do is you need to
know that רגל Regel pays full damages in רשות הניזק. Reshut HaNizak.
So the קל וחומר Kal Vachomer. is like this. תם Tam pays
half כופר Kofer. in רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak, so
pay full כופר... Kofer. I'm sorry, תם Tam pays half כופר Kofer.
in רשות הרבים, Reshut HaRabim,
should קל וחומר kal vachomer pay full כופר Kofer. in רשות הניזק?
Reshut HaNizak? Why? Because a רגל Regel pays no damages in רשות
הרבים Reshut HaRabim and pays full damages in רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak,
so a תם that pays half כופר Kofer in רשות הרבים Reshut
HaRabim should certainly pay full כופר Kofer in רשות הניזק. Reshut HaNizak.
Okay, but now it's already a little apples and oranges. Just cause
it's
weightier by נזק nezek doesn't mean it's weightier by כופר, Kofer. which
is what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, no that doesn't really work. מה לנזיקין דרגל
שכן ישנן באש? Mah leNezikin deRegel sheken yeshnan beEish? So... I'm sorry,
ולפרוך, Velifroch, why not challenge that? ומה לנזיקין דרגל שכן ישנן באש?
Umah leNezikin deRegel sheken yeshnan beEish? No, no, no. You can't say
that רגל Regel, is weightier.
You can't say that from damages of רגל Regel you can infer
כופר, Kofer
because
רגל, Regel when you're in a world of damages, damages like even
by a fire do you pay for normal damages, okay, but by
a fire you don't pay for כופר. Kofer. So things you pay
for damages for like רגל Regel are not relevant to כופר, Kofer.
because there's other... because we know like you pay for damages for
fire and you don't pay for כופר. kofer. So the fact that
you pay for damages for רגל Regel in רשות הניזק Reshut HaNizak
doesn't prove what your כופר kofer payments will be. שכן ישנן באש.
Sheken yeshnan beEish. So the גמרא Gemara says מטמון? MiTamon? Oh how
about something that's hidden? We'll find out later that if you have
something hidden in a haystack and the fire burns it you're not
liable, okay. So the argument would be like this, if the רגל
Regel, pays full damages in רשות הניזק Reshut HaNizak and therefore כופר
kofer should be full in רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak, so the גמרא
Gemara says and if you're going to challenge... and רגל Regel pays
full damages even when it breaks something that's buried. So you can't
say, well, an אש Eish pays damages and doesn't pay כופר kofer.
because an אש Eish wouldn't pay damages in that case. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, מה לטמון שכן ישנו בבור? Mah leTamon
sheken yeshno beBor? But if something is buried you'd be חייב chayav
if something was hidden, we'll find out later, buried in a load
or something and fell into a בור. Bor. So you could still
say look, you can't go from damages to
כופר. kofer You pay for damages for something buried in a haystack,
you pay for it for רגל, Regel you pay for it for
בור, Bor, but you don't go ahead and you don't pay for
that for a case of כופר. kofer בור Bor doesn't pay for
כופר. kofer So just because something is going to have you paying
for damages doesn't mean you're going to be paying for it for
כופר. kofer So the גמרא Gemara says מכלים. MiKeilim. Okay, how about
if it's vessels? Vessels you're exempt on a בור. Bor. שור ולא
אדם חמור ולא כלים. Shor velo Adam chamor velo keilim. And therefore
the argument would be like this: if a רגל Regel breaks vessels
in רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak, it's חייב נזק שלם chayav Nezek Shalem
and therefore you should go ahead and you should also pay
full כופר kofer for
קרן. keren And
you'll challenge that and you're going to
just say a
בור Bor pays for damages and not for כופר kofer because a
בור Bor wouldn't pay for כלים. Keilim. So therefore you have something
that you're going to pay for damages and therefore you should certainly
be paying for כופר. kofer And don't say ah, there's a בור
Bor case or an אש Eish case where you pay for damages
and you don't pay for כופר kofer because we're talking about circumstances
where you wouldn't pay them for בור Bor or אש Eish either.
So the גמרא Gemara says מה לכלים שכן ישנן באש? Mah leKeilim
sheken yeshnan beEish? No, but at least the כלים Keilim case you
would pay for fire. So the גמרא Gemara says מכלים טמונים. MiKeilim
tmunim. Okay, buried כלים. Keilim. So you've got a case of a
רגל regel that stomps on buried כלים Keilim in רשות הניזק Reshut
HaNizak and you're still חייב. chayav And if you're חייב chayav, for
that in רשות הניזק, Reshut HaNizak, you should certainly be paying full
כופר. kofer: That's the קל וחומר. kal vachomer And don't tell me
that
there are the cases that you're חייב בנזק chayav beNezek and פטור
בכופר, patur beKofer, like בור Bor and אש, Eish, because in this
case of כלים טמונים, Keilim tmunim, of buried כלים, Keilim, you're exempt
by בור Bor and אש. Eish. So there isn't a case where
you're
חייב, chayav there's not a counterexample, ah, I can prove to you
you're חייב בנזק chayav beNezek and פטור בכופר. patur beKofer. Because we're
picking a very specific case of כלים טמונים Keilim tmunim where you're
actually פטור patur in בור Bor and אש. Eish. And still you're
חייב chayav in רגל regel, and therefore you're going to be חייב
chayav in כופר. kofer, Okay, גמרא Gemara says one minute, מה לכלים
טמונים שכן ישנן באדם? Mah leKeilim tmunim sheken yeshnan beAdam? כלים טמונים
kelim temunim at least if a person damage כלים טמונים, kelim temunim,
you're חייב, chayav, but you're פטור patur in כופר. kofer. So the
fact that you're חייב chayav in כלים טמונים kelim temunim by רגל
regel does not prove that you're חייב chayav in כופר kofer because
you have an אדם adam. that's חייב chayav in כלים טמונים kelim
temunim and it's going to and an אדם adam. is, as we
said before, פטור patur in כופר kofer in כופר. kofer אלא לאו
שמע מינה מכופר דרגל מייתי לה עלמא איכא כופר ברגל שמע מינה.
Ela lav shemama mina mikofer de-regel mayseela alma ika kofer beregel shemama
mina.
So it must be that you learn it out from כופר kofer
of רגל, regel that כופר kofer of רגל regel you're חייב, chayav
that is a good proof. So that was a little more than
a little complicated, but the basic point was the following.
If you say קרן keren is half כופר kofer, in רשות הרבים,
reshus harabim, you could say it's full כופר kofer in רשות הניזק
reshus hanizak if you have רגל regel being חייב chayav in כופר
kofer. in רשות הניזק. reshus hanizak. Then it's apples and apples. You're
חייב chayav full כופר kofer for רגל regel in רשות הניזק, reshus
hanizak, you should be חייב chayav full כופר kofer for קרן keren
in רשות הניזק. reshus hanizak. Very simple. If the case of רגל
regel. is only a case of נזיקין, nezikin. you can't make the
jump of apples and oranges from you're חייב chayav in full נזק
nezek you should be חייב chayav in כופר kofer because there's all
these ways in things that are חייב chayav. in נזק nezek and
פטור patur in
כופר: kofer אש esh and בור bor and אדם; adam and even
though we tried to get rid of those exceptions, they don't go
away. They're cases that you're חייב chayav. in נזק nezek and פטור
patur in כופר, kofer so therefore it cannot be doing the jump
from נזק nezek to כופר. kofer It must be that רגל regel
itself is חייב chayav in כופר kofer in רשות הניזק reshus hanizak
and therefore we can make the קל וחומר to say קרן keren
is חייב chayav in כופר kofer in רשות הניזק reshus hanizak also
for רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. And now the גמרא Gemara says the
easiest thing it should have said from the beginning about trying to
make the apples and oranges comparison. The גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה
רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא, Amar lei Rav Acha midifti le-Ravina, רב אחא
מדפתי Rav Acha midifti said to רבינא, Ravina, הכי נמי מסתברא דאיכא
כופר ברגל. Hachi nami mistavra de-ika kofer beregel.
You know what, you're right. You had to say that if we're
going to say full קרן keren? for רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon full
כופר kofer in רשות הניזק, reshus hanizak, it's because there's כופר kofer
for רגל. regel דאי סלקא דעתך דליכא כופר ברגל, De-isalka daitach d'leika
kofer beregel, if there weren't כופר kofer ברגל beregel ותני מנזיקין דרגל
מייתי לה, ve-tani mi-nezekin de-regel mayseela, and we are trying to mix
apples and oranges and say because you pay full damages in רשות
הניזק reshus hanizak you should pay full כופר, so then we should
have challenged that basic apples and oranges directly. Forget going to בור
bor and אש esh and אדם. What we should have said is
לפרוך, lifroch,
why not challenge it and say מה לנזיקין דרגל שכן ישנן ברגל.
mah le-nezekin de-regel she-kein yeshnan beregel.
It should have said you can't go from נזק nezek, of רגל
regel to כופר because רגל regel, itself doesn't pay כופר. You know,
so therefore רגל regel. applies to רגל, regel but כופר doesn't apply
to רגל. regel, So that should have been the biggest question. How
can you say, oh, if you pay full damages for רגל regel
you should pay full כופר for קרן? keren? You don't even pay
כופר for רגל, regel, so how can you jump from damages of
רגל regel. to קרן? keren.
So אלא לאו שכן ישנן ברגל, ela lav she-kein yeshnan beregel, that's
only by רגל, regel. כופר isn't by
רגל. regel, אלא שמע מינה מכופר דרגל מייתי לה, Ela shemama mina
mikofer de-regel mayseela, if you're going to make a קל וחומר it
must be from כופר of רגל. regel, You pay full כופר of
רגל, regel, you should pay full כופר of of of קרן. keren
עלמא איכא כופר ברגל, Alma ika kofer beregel, you see that there
is כופר by רגל, שמע מינה shemama mina you do see that
and presumably that's even according to the רבנן Rabbanan who disagree with
רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon just says that they
would agree that there's כופר by רגל, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon would
just say, ay I hold this half כופר in רשות הרבים reshus
harabim which the רבנן Rabbanan could disagree with or do disagree with
like רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, and then basing on רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili of a full כופר in רשות הניזק.
reshus hanizak. Okay, so that is the end of רבי טרפון and
דיו. And now we begin the next משנה. Mishnah.
אדם מועד לעולם בין שוגג בין מזיד. Adam muad leolam bein shogeg
bein mazed. So this is the fifth of the five things that
are מועד. muad. Number four was the, you know, רבי טרפון's קרן
in רשות הניזק reshus hanizak and number five is אדם. אדם מועד
לעולם. Adam muad leolam. A person is always מועד. muad. A person
always pays full damages. בין שוגג בין מזיד, Bein shogeg bein mazed,
whether intentional or unintentional, בין ער בין ישן, bein er bein yashen,
whether he is awake or asleep. Now actually by asleep, you know,
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says that that's only if he goes to sleep
and the vessels are near him. If somebody puts a vessel near
him after he already went to sleep, then he is exempt. Now
why is he exempt? Is it true that a person is always
liable, a hundred percent, absolute responsibility?
Maybe. And then why would you be exempt if somebody put a
vessel near you and you were asleep? Well, that would be because
of a counterbalancing פשיעת הניזק, peshias hanizak, contributory negligence. It's not that
you were not negligent, you as the human don't need to be
negligent at all, you could be completely against, you know, no fault,
no blame, but you broke it you pay for it. But if
I put the vessel near you, then I have more active negligence
and therefore it's my responsibility. You know, if it's my vessel or
somebody else's vessel whatever, I am the one that takes that responsibility
away from you. But if let's say you went to sleep and
the wind blew a vessel near you and it was nobody's fault
and you rolled over and broke it, you're... would be liable אדם
מועד לעולם. Adam Muad L'olam. That's one explanation. תוספות, Tosfos, that's the
רמב"ן's Ramban approach. תוספות Tosfos says אדם מועד לעולם Adam Muad L'olam
means really just
for you don't need a lot of negligence, but you still do
need a certain degree and when you go to sleep near a
vessel, there's a certain degree of negligence. Not the simple sense of
the משנה. Mishna. Okay. בין ער בין ישן, Bein eir bein yashen,
whether awake or asleep, סימא את עין חבירו ושיבר את הכלים, sima
es ein chaveiro v'shibar es hakeilim, if while you were asleep you
blinded somebody God forbid or you broke a vessel, משלם נזק שלם,
meshalem nezek shaleim, you pay full damages because אדם מועד לעולם. Adam
Muad L'olam. So now the גמרא Gemara. says like this, קתני סימא
את עין חבירו דומיא דשיבר את הכלים. Katani sima es ein chaveiro
dumya d'shibar es hakeilim.
We taught this idea of blinding somebody similar to breaking a vessel.
מה התם נזק אין ארבעה דברים לא, mah hatam nezek in arba'ah
devarim lo, the same way by a vessel, since it's just an
object, it's all you have is just damages. You don't have doctors'
bills and pain, etc., etc. אף סימא את עין חבירו נזק אין
ארבעה דברים לא. af sima es ein chaveiro nezek in arba'ah devarim
lo. The same is true when you injure somebody, okay, the fact
that אדם מועד לעולם Adam Muad L'olam and that's absolute liability even
if you're not negligent, that's only about the payment of the basic
damages like you would do if you broke an object. The other
payments that are unique to injuring a person, צער ריפוי שבת ובושת,
tza'ar ripui sheves u'voshes, that you need a degree of negligence. If
you look at רש"י, Rashi רש"י Rashi says נזק אין ארבעה דברים
לא, nezek in arba'ah devarim lo, דלא מחייב ארבעה דברים אלא מזיד
או קרוב למזיד d'lo mechayev arba'ah devarim ela meizid o karov l'meizid
דומיא דחרופין. dumya d'chrufin. You have to be either intentional or close
to being intentional like the פסוק pasuk, when two people fight and
accidentally one person goes in and grabs the privates of the other
person and that's where we learn out בושת boshes and so on.
So that's where there's a lot of intentionality even though that particular
act of grabbing the privates or
whatever might not have been
exactly intended or so on. So but it's close to being intentional,
קרוב למזיד. karov l'meizid. So that is going to be very important.
At one extreme אדם מועד לעולם Adam Muad L'olam might be even
absolute liability, no blame at all but you still have to pay.
Nobody's blaming you but you still are liable. Okay, that's for the
damages and for the ארבעה דברים, arba'ah devarim, is it negligence enough?
It doesn't sound like that. It sounds like you need real intentionality
or רש"י Rashi says קרוב למזיד, karov l'meizid, close to being intentional.
We'll see more about that. Let's take a look now top of
כ"ו עמוד ב'. Chaf-Vav Amud Beis. מנא הני מילי? Mina hanei milei?
Where does this come from? אמר חזקיה וכן תנא דבי חזקיה, Amar
Chizkiyah v'chein tana d'vei Chizkiyah, חזקיה Chizkiyah said and it was also
taught from חזקיה's Chizkiyah ישיבה, yeshiva, אמר קרא, the פסוק pasuk, says
פצע תחת פצע, petza tachas petza, a wound for a wound. Okay.
לחייבו על השוגג כמזיד. L'chayvo al hashogeg k'meizid. That extra פסוק, pasuk.
there's a lot of things. פצע תחת פצע, petza tachas petza, עין
תחת עין, שן תחת שן, we learn a lot of things from
that. So one of the things that we learn from פצע תחת
פצע, petza tachas petza, which is where we learn basic payment for
damages for injuring a person is to tell you under all circumstances
even if you're blameless. שוגג כמזיד shogeg k'meizid ועל אונס כרצון, v'al
ones k'ratzon, even if it's completely against your will it's like that
you did it willfully. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, האי
מיבעי ליה ליתן צער במקום נזק, hai mibaei lei litten tza'ar bimkom
nezek, don't we need that to tell you another הלכה? halacha? To
tell you a הלכה halacha that even when you're paying damages you
also have to pay for the pain that accompanies it. Meaning you
can pay צער tza'ar if there was no נזק, nezek like you
burned somebody, the example is on the fingernail, and it caused enormous
pain but there was no damage
in terms of the person wasn't worth any less. So and that's
צער שלא במקום נזק, tza'ar shelo bimkom nezek, and this is צער
במקום נזק. tza'ar bimkom nezek. You actually God forbid I don't know
you knocked out his eye, you broke his arm, so there was
damages you have to pay for and you have to pay for
the pain. And that idea that it comes even accompanying the payment
of נזק nezek, we learn from פצע תחת פצע. petza tachas petza.
So the גמרא Gemara, says no, אם כן לכתוב קרא פצע בפצע.
im kein lichtig kra petza b'petza. It could have said a wound
for a wound. מאי תחת? mai tachas? In the stead of פצע?
petza? שמע מינה תרתי, shma mina tarti, you learn both out. Okay.
Interestingly, even though both are learned out from the פסוק, the idea
that you have strict liability is only going to be for the
נזק, nezek. not for the צער. The צער still has to be
מזיד meizid or קרוב למזיד karov l'meizid and תוספות Tosfos says that's
because we have a general inclination to say that because it's
such a high degree of obligation, strict liability, we're going to limit
it only to the one case that it clearly applies to which
is the נזק. nezek All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this,
if you take a look at תוספות שמע מינה תרתי Tosfos shma
mina tarti in the middle he says ויש אומרים דכל מה דמצינן
למפטר שוגג פטרינן, v'yeish omrim d'chol mah d'matzinan l'miftar shogeg patrinan, that
we want to exempt you if you're not to blame and therefore
this idea of high liability and strict liability we'll limit only to
the case we have to apply it to, which is for the
נזק nezek itself, not for the ארבעה דברים. arba'ah devarim.
Okay. אמר רבה. Amar Rabbah. Now we're going to have a series
of teachings of רבה, Rabbah, going to be very interesting. Says רבה,
Rabbah, היתה אבן מונחת לו בחיקו ולא הכיר בה ועמד ונפלה. Hayta
even munachas lo b'cheiko v'lo hikir bah v'amad v'nafla.
A guy was on a roof and there was a stone on
his chest and he never knew about it while he was sleeping
somebody put a stone on his chest. And he woke up and
he stood up and he stood up and the stone fell off
of his chest and fell down and broke something. לענין נזיקין חייב.
L'inyan nezikin chayav. If it went ahead And it broke something on
the ground, you're חייב. chayav. That seems to be a perfect example
of like strict liability. He is completely blameless and still he's חייב.
chayav. But what's also actually interesting is he didn't even do it
with his body, right? He did it with his כח. koach. And
you might say that the כח koach that was completely unaware is
sort of like חצי נזק צרורות, chatzi nezek tzororos, right? Completely unaware
that this is happening as a result of me, maybe it's not
even considered to be me doing it. So that's another חידוש, chiddush,
that even through his כח, koach, this is אדם doing it, and
even an unaware כח, koach, and he's strictly liable and he pays.
לעניין ארבעה דברים פטור. L'inyan arba'ah devarim patur. And certainly נזק צער
ריפוי שבת בושת, nezek tza'ar ripuy sheves boshes, as we said, obviously
you're פטור. patur. לעניין שבת, L'inyan Shabbos, if it went ahead and
the stone went, I don't know, from רשות הרבים reshus harabim to
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, let's say, מלאכת
מחשבת אסרה תורה, meleches machsheves osrah Torah,
you're פטור. patur. It's not an intentional act. By שבת Shabbos it
has to be מלאכת מחשבת meleches machsheves like the משכן. Mishkan. It
has to be intentional. This is completely not intentional. It's pretty obvious.
We'll get to cases which are less obvious. לעניין גלות, L'inyan galus,
if it killed somebody, פטור. patur. You're also פטור. patur. Why? Because
it says מכה נפש בשגגה. makeh nefesh bishgagah. There has to be
a שגגה, shgagah, some type of negligence, right? Not something that's completely
an אונס. oness. Okay, something that you at least had some awareness
of. לעניין עבד, L'inyan eved,
let's say knocked out the tooth of a slave, would the slave
go free? פלוגתא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל ורבנן. Plugta d'Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel v'rabanan. That's a debate of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel and the רבנן. rabanan. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braisa, הרי שהיה רבו רופא ואמר לו כחול עיני וסימאה, harei
shehayah rabo rofey v'omar lo k'chol einay v'sim'ah,
that the slave said to the master, "Would you like, you know,
give me some eye treatment, eye salve," and in the process of
doing it, the master accidentally blinded the slave. חתור לי שיני, Chator
li shinay, or you know, would you mind up you know made
a filling in my tooth, okay, והפילה, v'hipilah, accidentally caused the tooth
to come out. So he was actually trying to help the slave,
but in the end the eye came out and the tooth came
out. שיחק באדון ויצא לחירות. shichek b'adon v'yatza l'cheirus. תנא קמא Tanna
kamma says you laugh at the master and you go free. Doesn't
matter according to them, even if it was completely not intentional. I
mean, there was a degree of intention to be doing something to
the eye, but anyway, seems like completely not intentional. The master caused
the eye to go out or the tooth to go out, the
slave is free. You don't need any intention. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר ושיחתה. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer v'shichasah. No, you destroyed it,
says the פסוק. עד שיתכוין לשחתה. ad sheyiskayvein l'shachasah. You have to
try to actually be knocking it out. All right, so he requires
a high degree of intention. So for the רבנן, rabanan, the slave
would go free, and for רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel, obviously not.
Okay, now that's case one. Case number two. הכיר בה ושכחה. Hikir
boh v'shichachah. You knew the stone was on your chest and you
forgot about it, and then you stood up and all these things
happened again.
ועמד ונפלה. v'omad v'noflah. And you stood up and it fell. לעניין
נזיקין חייב. L'inyan nezikin chayav. Obviously you're חייב chayav by נזיקין. nezikin
You were חייב chayav, even when you were unaware. לעניין ארבעה דברים
פטור. L'inyan arba'ah devarim patur. You're still פטור patur for ארבעה דברים,
arba'ah devarim, even though there was a degree of negligence, it's not
what רש"י Rashi calls מזיד או קרוב למזיד. meizid o karov l'meizid.
Okay, there was some degree of negligence. לעניין גלות חייב. L'inyan galus
chayav. If it went and killed somebody, you're חייב. chayav You knew
about it, there was awareness, there was negligence. דאמר קרא בשגגה. d'omar
kra bishgagah. בשגגה Bishgagah
means that there had to be an initial awareness that you're dealing
with something dangerous or whatever, you know, and there was an initial
awareness, okay, and now you were negligent and you're חייב. chayav והוי
ליה ידיעה. V'havei lay yediah. He had an awareness. לעניין שבת פטור.
L'inyan Shabbos patur. By שבת Shabbos, you're not חייב chayav. for negligence.
For שבת Shabbos, to be a מלאכה, melacha, it has to be
מלאכת מחשבת. meleches machsheves. You have to intentionally carry something and you
did not now transport this
intentionally from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid to רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. You
didn't intentionally want to do this act. Okay, negligence, yes; intention, no.
לעניין עבד פלוגתא דרבן שמעון בן גמליאל ורבנן. L'inyan eved plugta d'Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel v'rabanan. And for the slave, again the debate of
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and the רבנן. rabanan.
It was negligent, it wasn't intentional. For the רבנן, rabanan, even if
it's completely not negligent, he goes free, you knocked out his eye.
And for רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, only until
it's intentional.
Now. נתכוין לזרוק שתיים וזרק ארבע. Niskayvein lizrok shtayim v'zorak arba. Let's
say you took, had this stone, and you tried to throw it
two אמות, amos, and you threw it four אמות. amos. And four
אמות, amos, by the way, for שבת, Shabbos is carrying, four אמות
amos in רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Okay, but let's say also there
was a man standing four אמות amos away, and you were trying
to throw it only two אמות, amos, but it went further and
it hit the man four אמות. amos. So again, לעניין נזיקין חייב.
l'inyan nezikin chayav. For נזיקין you're חייב, chayav you're חייב chayav, even
if you're an
אונס. oness. לעניין ארבעה דברים פטור. L'inyan arba'ah devarim patur. ארבעה דברים
Arba'ah devarim you're פטור patur again. Maybe there was a degree of
negligence. If I threw it two, it might have gone four, but
that's not enough to make you מזיד או קרוב למזיד. meizid o
karov l'meizid. It's no different than forgetting the stone was on your
chest. You're פטור. patur. לעניין שבת, L'inyan Shabbos, when it comes to
שבת, Shabbos מלאכת מחשבת בעינן. meleches machsheves ba'inan.
Again you need מלאכת מחשבת meleches machsheves and therefore you were not
trying to do an act of carrying. Moving something two אמות amos
in רשות הרבים reshus harabim is not considered an act of carrying.
It wound up going four אמות, amos, which is considered an act
of
carrying, but your intent was not to do a מלאכה. melacha. Even
though a מלאכה melacha was done, you did not do a מלאכה.
melacha. Okay, לעניין גלות, l'inyan galus, when it comes to גלות, galus
אשר לא צדה. asher lo tzadah. אשר לא צדה אמר רחמנא, asher
lo tzada amar rachmana, that you did not lie in wait, says
the תורה, פרט לנתכוון לזרוק שתיים וזרק ארבע, prat leniskaivain lizrok shtayim
vezarak arba, to exclude the case of two and four. Now רש"י
Rashi has two readings of this. One reading of רש"י Rashi is
אשר לא צדה asher lo tzada being lying in wait is when
you're doing it intentionally and you get and you get executed. So
according to this רש"י Rashi. is saying is you're not the case
of doing it intentionally, you only tried to do four. Like let's
say, you know, you shot an arrow and you thought it was
going to hit the ground before it hit the guy and it
went so far and it hit the guy. So even though you
were playing with a loaded weapon, you weren't actually trying to kill
him, so you're not חייב מיתה, chayav misa, but because you went
ahead and you did kill him, you are חייב בגלות. chayav begalus.
So this is a little bit of a not natural read of
the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara; has been talking not about חייב
מיתה chayav misa but חייב גלות. chayav galus. But this way of
reading it is actually saying you're חייב גלות. chayav galus. You were
negligent with this person's death. The other way of reading it, which
more fits the language of the גמרא, is that you're פטור patur
from גלות galus. because you're too negligent. Okay, meaning that if you're
shooting a loaded weapon, you're throwing a stone, you're shooting an arrow,
whatever, even though you're not trying to hit the person, that is
too close to the idea of אשר לא צדה asher lo tzada
of being lying in wait that you are actually too much of
an act that's close to murder and it's not just negligent when
you're being, you know, innocent and chopping wood and so on. So
your negligence or maybe better say your intentionality is too great and
therefore actually you are פטור patur for גלות. galus Okay. לעניין עבד,
le-inyan eved, now when it comes to the slave we're back to
where we were. מחלוקת רבן שמעון בן גמליאל ורבנן, machlokes Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel ve-rabbanan, even it's a still the debate of רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל ורבנן, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel ve-rabbanan, even though you're throwing
something two and the guy is only four אמות amos away and
it's a reasonable likelihood or who knows what possible it might go
and hit him, you are not intending to knock out his tooth,
so for רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel you're still
the עבד eved does not go free, for רבנן rabbanan the עבד
eved still goes free.
Now לזרוק ארבע וזרק שמונה, lizrok arba vezarak shmona, let's say you
tried to throw it four אמות amos and it went eight. Now
for everything else it's identical, the only thing that's different because you
know who cares, if we're talking about hurting a guy hitting a
guy you tried to throw it away that was not going to
get him but he was right in front of you and it
went further it hit him, same degree of
negligence etc. The difference will be for שבת Shabbos because throwing something
ארבע אמות arba amos for שבת is already a מלאכה. melacha. So
you were trying to do a מלאכה melacha but the מלאכה melacha
got done in a slightly different way and it went eight
אמות. amos. Okay. לעניין נזיקין חייב, le-inyan nezikin chayav, so you're חייב
chayav, for נזק because that's absolute liability. לעניין ארבעה דברים פטור, le-inyan
arba’ah devarim patur, you're פטור patur for ארבעה דברים arba’ah devarim because
even though even this which is a surprise is not considered מזיד
or קרוב למזיד. karov le-meizid. Even though the guy's standing right there
since you were trying to make it land before it hit the
guy, that's not considered קרוב למזיד, karov le-meizid, which is pretty surprising.
Okay. לעניין ארבעה דברים פטור, le-inyan arba’ah devarim patur, same as with
the two and the four case. לעניין שבת, le-inyan Shabbos, שבת is
the one thing that's different. באומר כל מקום שתרצה תנוח אין אי
לאו לא. be-omer kol makom she-tirtze tanuach in i lo lo. If
you say I'm throwing it out at four but I really don't
care where it lands, then you're חייב. chayav, Okay, but if you
really say no I דווקא davka want it to land at ארבע
אמות, arba amos, then even then you are פטור, patur, even though
you intended to do a מלאכה, melacha, the מלאכה melacha was done
in a different way than you wanted. But if you're okay wherever
it lands, that would be included in מלאכת מחשבת. meleches machsheves. לעניין
גלות אשר לא צדה פרט לנתכוון לזרוק ארבע וזרק שמונה, le-inyan galus
asher lo tzada prat leniskaivain lizrok arba vezarak shmona, for גלות galus
we'll read it the second way of רש"י. Rashi This is a
degree of intentionality because you were throwing something in his direction, so
therefore you are פטור patur for גלות because it's not a total
accident and there's too much intentionality here. לעניין עבד מחלוקת רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל ורבנן, le-inyan eved machlokes Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel ve-rabbanan, and
the עבד eved again it's a debate over רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and the Rabbis. Okay, so that was really
interesting putting all those different types of things together and allowing us
to explore that even, you know, two and four and four and
eight is not enough negligence intentionality to be חייב chayav? for ארבעה
דברים. arba’ah devarim. ואמר רבה, ve-amar Rabbah, one last case, רבה Rabbah
also says זרק
כלי מראש הגג ובא אחר ושיברו במקל, zarak kli merosh hagag u-va
acher ve-shibro be-makel, you threw a vessel, we saw this earlier, off
the top of a roof and somebody came and it broke it
with a stick before it hit the ground. פטור, patur, you're exempt.
מאי טעמא? mai ta’ama? Why? מנא תבירא תבר, mana sevira tevar, because
you broke something that was already broken. When the guy threw it
off the roof, okay, it was going in its way and the
gravity and it would have been destroyed so it was considered worthless,
it was considered broken. So the guy who broke it with a
stick did not do anything, you know, was not liable, you know,
did not break a vessel that was worth anything. And the guy
who threw it off the roof, you know, it's interesting question, sounds
like he's also פטור patur because he never broke it. So that
would be a very unfortunate outcome for the owner of the vessel,
but that's the irony here. Okay. מנא תבירא
תבר. mana sevira tevar. אמר רבה, amar Rabbah, רבה Rabbah says זרק
כלי מראש הגג והיו תחתיו כרים וכסתות. zarak kli merosh hagag ve-hayu
tachtav karim u-chesasos.
If you threw a vessel off of a roof and underneath it
were pillows, so when you threw it off you weren't exactly you
weren't going to do anything, you know, it wasn't going to break.
So you weren't liable for throwing it off. ובא אחר וסילקן, u-va
acher ve-silkan, and somebody came and removed the pillows, או קדם הוא
וסילקן, o kidem hu ve-silkan, or you yourself came and removed the
pillows, פטור, patur, you're exempt. מאי טעמא? mai ta’ama? What's the reason?
בעידנא דשדייה be-idna de-shadyai When you threw it off the roof, your
arrows were already ended, meaning that was not an act of damaging
because you were not doing an act that was not going to
break it; it was going to hit the pillows. You can't be
liable for throwing it off the roof, and for removing the pillows
you're not liable because that's גרמא, grama, you didn't do an act
of damage, you just removed
pillows, and גרמא בנזיקין פטור. grama be-nezikin patur. We'll see later on
about גרמי garmi and other things, but anyway, that's going to be
exempt. And even if you did both parts, you're פטור patur for
throwing and you're פטור patur for pulling it out. Now,
the sum total is you're פטור. patur. It does sound, since he
didn't give the case of you yourself with the stick in the
second case, it does sound like if you threw it off the
roof and then broke it with a stick you'd be חייב, chayav
because your throwing off the roof was מחייב mechayev you and it
broke at the end and it wasn't somebody else who broke it.
All right, now the גמרא continues and says the following: ואמר רבה
ve-amar Rabbah זרק תינוק מראש הגג. zarak tinok me-rosh ha-gag. And this
is the case that we'll end with.
By the way, I should say if you look at רש"י Rashi
by the case of throwing it off the roof and somebody breaking
it with a stick, רש"י Rashi says פטור זה ששיברו במקל, patur
ze she-shibro be-makel, the one who broke it with the stick is
פטור, patur, קודם שיצאה שנפלה להישבר. kodem she-yatza she-sofah le-hishaver. It sounds
from רש"י Rashi that the guy who threw it off the roof
is חייב, since even if somebody else broke it with a stick,
since when I threw it off the roof it was going to
break and that was considered, remember the גמרא before also whether
בשר דארמנא, basar d'armana, מעיקרא דארמנא, me'ikara d'armana, that was if it
miraculously got saved that would be different. But since when I threw
it off the roof it was going to break and it broke
even if it broke through other causes I would still be חייב,
that's at least what רש"י sounds like in the first case of
רבא. Rava. Last case of רבה Rabbah rather, last case of רבה
Rabbah that we'll do for today:
ואמר רבה ve-amar Rabbah זרק תינוק מראש הגג. zarak tinok me-rosh ha-gag.
If a person threw a baby, God forbid, an infant off of
a roof ובא אחר וקיבלו בסייף u-va acher ve-kiblo be-sa'if and somebody
came and speared it with a sword, it's horrific, sounds like what
the Nazis did, ימח שמם, yimach shemam,
and before the baby hit the ground, so who is חייב? Can
you prosecute either party for רציחה? retzicha? פלוגתא דרבי יהודה בן בתירא
ורבנן, plugta de-Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira ve-rabanan, the debate of רבי יהודה
בן בתירא Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira and the Rabbis at the time
we turned in a ברייתא: Beraita: הכהו עשרה בני אדם בעשרה מקלות
בין בבת אחת בין בזה אחר זה כולם פטורים. hikahu asara bnei
adam be-asara maklot bein be-vat achat bein be-ze achar ze kulam pturim.
Ten people hit somebody with ten sticks and the person died; whether
they did it sequentially or at the same time, they're exempt. We
had this earlier in the גמרא; it's a complicated case. Did each
one have the ability to kill him? Was it only being able
to be killed through the cumulative effect of all of them? רבי
יהודה בן בתירא אומר, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer, top of כ"ז
עמוד א': kaf zayin amud aleph: בזה אחר זה האחרון חייב מפני
שקירב מיתתו. be-ze achar ze ha-acharon chayav mipnei she-keirev mitato. When one
after the other, the last one is חייב because he was the
one that actually finalized, finished it off. So it sounds like to
compare it to this case of רבה Rabbah that each one of
these could have done it themselves. So maybe it's easier to think
about it with shooting with a gun rather than with a stick.
Ten people shoot somebody at the exact same time. Since any one
of them could have committed murder you can't be מחייב mechayev any
of them. That's one way of saying it.
Whereas if it's sequential, ten people shot sequentially but the person hadn't
died yet at all until the end, so then also the Rabbis
would say well anyone of them could have done it and he
didn't die and at the end he died and all of them
did it equally, who are you going to be מחייב? mechayev? Whereas
רבי יהודה בן בתירא Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira would say no, the
last guy who did it, he was we put it on him,
even if the other ones were fatal, it was the last one
who did it. So if that at least works and maps onto
רבה's Rabbah case, one guy threw it off, it would have been
fatal, the other guy did the final fatal thing, do you say
two people murdered the baby? Do you say it's only the last
one? Okay, pretty horrific to contemplate, anyway, that is where we will
end for today.